## **Poppy Nicolette Riddle**

6419 Liverpool Street Halifax, Nova Scotia Canada B3P 1B1 email: poppy.riddle@dal.ca mobile:782 414 7740

**Profile** 

Having just completed a Master of Information Management degree at Dalhousie University, I research scholarly production and information visualization as an Interdisciplinary PhD student. I have a long history as an artist, maker, and designer and love sharing the joy of making with others. I am an activist for 2SLGBTQIA+ rights and increasing representation. As a mid-career academic, I look forward to opportunities to research and apply design thinking to solutions for academic libraries and their information seekers.

Education

Dalhousie University, School of Information Management
Master of Information Management, anticipated graduation in May 2022
California College of the Arts
BFA - Industrial Design Program, Honors, 2010

Peer reviewed publications

Riddle, P. (2022). A visual analysis method comparing keywords from two search results using keyword co-occurrences, Thesis. Dalhousie University, Halifax, Canada. Taylor et al., (2022). Ted's Teas: A Two-part Accounting and Audit 'Cross-over Case, submitted manuscript. Dalhousie University, Halifax, Canada. Riddle, P. et al., (2021). The State of OA in the U15 Canadian Academic Repositories, work in progress. Dalhousie University, SIM, Halifax, Canada.

Reports

Riddle, P. et al., (2021). Report on State of the Art of CO2 Management Strategies for the Dalhousie Office of Sustainability. Dalhousie University, Halifax, Canada. Riddle, P., Charlebois, S., Music, J. (2021). Tipping in Canada report. Dalhousie University, Halifax, Canada.

**Presentations** 

Taylor, S. et al. (2022). The Evolution of Teaching Effectiveness: a Bibliometric Perspective. Dalhousie Conference on University Teaching and Learning. Riddle, P. (2021). Comparing search terms for overlap and exclusions: a visual analysis. Dalhousie SIM Research Day.

Riddle, P. (2021). Keyword co-occurrence maps as visual analysis. LAMNS Conference. Riddle, P. (2021). Viewing information spatially. Dalhousie SIM Research Day.

**Editorials** 

Riddle, P. & Charlebois S. (2021). At the tipping point:... *The Conversation*.Riddle, P. (2021). Newspaper, radio, and television interviews, including CBC, The Star, and the National Post.

**Exhibitions** 

Riddle, N. (2014-2016). Products designed for TRP. Eurobike Exhibition. Riddle, N. (2000-2017). Products designed for multiple companies. Interbike Exhibition. Riddle, N. (2012). Handmade bicycle frame for TRP. NA Handmade Bicycle Show. Riddle, N. (2010) Exhibition of hand-made bicycle frames. San Jose Biennale. Riddle, N. (2010). Conflation 2010 (as member of collective). Playspace Gallery. Riddle, N. (2009) The Furniture Show. CCA Pop-Up Gallery.

Awards & Scholarships

Nova Scotia Graduate Scholarship, (\$15000/year for 4 years), 2022 CARL Graduate Research Grant, (awarded \$1000), 2022 Erudit/Coalition Publica Scholarship, (awarded \$5500), 2021 Faculty Development Grant, CCA, (awarded \$3000), 2016 Red Dot Awards - TRP Brakes / Tektro, 2016 Spark Awards - Sparse Lights, 2014 IF Awards - Echo Wheels, Easton, 2013 Student Leadership Award, 2009 & 2010 Finalist, James Dyson Award, 2009

All College Honors Award and Scholarship, 2009 Carmen M. Christensen Scholarships, 2007-2009

#### **Teaching Experience**

**Modelmaking** - Introduction to basic construction techniques and appropriate prototyping

**ID5** - Full semester project exploring the urban commute experience, student-initiated projects that resulted in speculative proposals for a future commute based on current technology.

**Urban Mobility Initiative** - designed summer intensive program centered on the the bicycle as a starting point for students to investigate social, ecological and methodological issues.

**Framebuilding 1-** Investigative studio in bicycle frame construction. Taught oxyacetylene torch use and safety, metal cutting principles, machine shop safety and use of the mill and lathe, bicycle frame design and construction, fillet brazing and refinement, painting and graphics.

**Advanced Geometry Fabrication** – An exploratory studio for new form generation software and natural fiber composites construction.

**ID1** - Introduction to human-centered design approach, concept development, modelmaking and presentation skills.

**ID2** - Project centered instruction to teach design methods and manufacturing techniques.

DC1 - Instruction in linear and non-linear elements of perspective for designers.

**3D Studio** - Graduate studio - sketching, idea generation techniques and prototyping.

#### **Academic Experience**

# Project Manager, Maritime Institute of Society, Technology & Society - 09/2121-current

Applications for external funding and exploratory research for future projects.

# Research Assistantships, Quantitative Science Studies Lab & Agri-Food Analytics Lab — 06/2020 to current

Apply Python to research projects for data cleaning, bibliometric analysis and visualization. Currently learning back-end databases and front-end deployments in Python environments. Contributed to scholarly production as principal investigator, and grant application writing.

### Practicum, assistant to Systems Librarian, NSCAD - 2021

Assessed the library's LibGuides for accessibility and use with screen readers. Provided written report of assessment, with map of action items for improvement, including ARIA.

# Assistant Professor, Industrial Design & First Year Dept., California College of the Arts – 2017 to 2020 (Sr. Lecturer from 2010 to 2016) San Francisco, CA

Teaching and curriculum development - Industrial Design and First Year students. Shop and technology liaison - Improved coordination between ID curriculum and shop resources, new tool and equipment recommendations, constructed tools and fixtures. Program expert - Performed portfolio reviews, transfer assessment and placement for ID Department in coordination with Academic Advisor and Admissions for the 2018/2019 academic year.

*Modelmaking* - Demonstrated safe use of materials, shop safety, wood working and metal working basics, and principles of tool sharpening. Introduced technical exercises coupled with inclusive-design methodology-based projects. Taught students the materials and rapid prototyping processes to communicate context and intent.

*Urban Mobility* - Initiated program in 2010 and have evolved curriculum to expand beyond traditional steel construction. Instructed and demonstrated bicycle frame building. Invited award-winning professionals to share their knowledge at class through demonstrations.

#### **Professional Experience**

# Freelance Design and Product Development Consultant – 2017 to 2020 Tiburon, CA

Concept to production development services - Supported clients such as GreenToys, TRP/Tektro, US Postal Service, Cognex Corporation, World Centric. Concept sketching and rapid prototyping – Communicated design explorations. CAD Model Development and iterative prototyping – Developed and managed complex electro-mechanical assemblies using multiple 3D printing methods for functional prototypes.

Communication and project coordination - Integrated international teams during development of complex electromechanical assemblies.

Design for Manufacturing – Worked collaboratively with suppliers to simplify and meet tooling cost goals, assembly processes, and define finish and color specifications. Injection molding, comolding, and electromechanical design features.

*Production development* - Created and maintained drawing packages, CAD files, supporting documentation and packaging to provide a product ready for the client.

# Director of Product Development, TRP USA / Tektro Brakes – 2012 to 2017 Ogden, Utah & Taichung, Taiwan

Strategy – Developed strategic plans with actions and measurable goals. Research & Intellectual Property – Created documentation of concepts for communication with legal team.

*Management & Partnerships* – Hired Jr. Mechanical Engineers and established partnerships with local higher education institutions.

*Concept development* – Created future concepts of bicycle components including sketch tools, clay, rapid prototyping, and CAD exploration.

*DFM and engineering* – Coordinated with Taiwan engineering team for injection molding, forging, die casting and CNC milling processes utilized for production.

*Documentation and marketing* - Utilized graphic design skills to create product catalogs for tradeshows, technical documentation such as owner's manuals, service guides and bulletins for distribution in print and web applications.

### **Product Development Engineer – 2010 to 2012**

Easton Bell Sports, Scotts Valley, CA

### Associate Engineer – 2003 to 2006

Fox Racing Shox, Inc. Watsonville, CA

### Engineering Manager - 2001 to 2003

Titec Cycles, USA Milpitas, CA

#### Research and Development Associate Engineer - 1997 to 2001

RockShox, Inc. Colorado Springs, CO 80907

**Intellectual Property** 

Patent application with World Centric on utensil dispenser, 2019

Patent applications with Tektro/TRP brakes for brake and lever related areas.

2 patent applications with Easton Bell Sports

Prio Paper Cast: 2009 Design Patent Application

Knowledge areas

Advanced literature searching skills & scholarly writing.

Open Access issues and education

Bibliometrics, scientometrics and altmetrics for individual and institutional evaluation

Python coding for data manipulation and data visualization

SQL and relational databases

Instructional Design and Instructional methodologies

Online Education Resources, LibGuides with accessibility for screen readers

Extensive product design experience including 2D sketching and 3D digital tools